Francisco Hernández

Full-stack Software Engineer

fjch87@gmail.com Portfolio +502 5126-9001 GitHub

Summary

Full-stack software engineer who specializes in building scalable, maintainable and fault resistant applications that create a great user experience using modern and in-demand technologies. I have a huge passion for programming, which I join with my technical knowledge to focus on delivering great software products. My repertoire includes programming languages and tools such as Python, JavaScript, TypeScript, ReactJS, Ionic, MUI, Node.js, Express.js, Next.js, MongoDB, PostgreSQL, and more.

Relevant experience

Software engineer @ Cognits (Project ShareGRO)

Sep 2021 - Jan 2023 // Guatemala, Guatemala

- Worked on the development of a customer facing and administrator web applications using HTML, CSS/SASS, TypeScript (React.js) and the Ionic framework.
- Implemented GraphQL API in a Node.js project using Express.js and express-graphql to serve queries and mutations for React.js applications and connected both using Apollo Client.
- Built endpoints in GraphQL API and implemented new features to extend back-end functionality in Python based project using Graphene-Python library and the Starlette framework.
- ▶ Implemented third party integrations for several services like SMS verification with Twilio, email sending with SendGrid, broker dealer services and financial services in Node.js and Python based projects.
- Built Node.js project and used the Serverless framework to declare AWS Lambda functions using TypeScript, with the purpose of having different cron-jobs that performed certain logic related with the user's information.
- Created the necessary infrastructure to host static builds of React.js applications and a containerized Express.js application using AWS S3, CloudFront, Route53, ECR and ECS.

Skills: TypeScript React.js Ionic CSS/SASS Python Graphene-Python Express.js MongoDB PostgreSQL Storybook Serverless Framework AWS (EC2, ECS, ECR, S3, CloudFront, Route53, Lambda Functions)

Software engineer @ Cognits (Project Onramp Invest)

Jul 2021 - Sep 2021 // Guatemala, Guatemala

- Gave support and developed new features to extend user experience functionality in existing front-end projects using JavaScript, Vue.js and CSS.
- Built new endpoints in existing REST API for data manipulation using FastAPI in Python based project.

Skills: JavaScript Node.js Vue.js Python FastAPI REST API

Software engineer @ Cognits (Project RLI Corp)

Mar 2021 - Sep 2021 // Guatemala, Guatemala

- Created necessary stylesheets using CSS/Sass to replicate quotation's web system for insurance company using the corresponding brand guidelines coming from Figma designs.
- Developed all the required API integrations in quotation's web system by following the given Swagger REST API documentation using the Mendix technology.

Skills: Java CSS/SASS Mendix Swagger Figma

Freelance Software engineer @ Pragmation

Jul 2021 - Aug 2021 // Guatemala, Guatemala

- Performed tasks to extend the functionality of online store of mobile airtime.
- Worked on the integration of Reloadly API into existing back-end application to perform actions such as buying mobile airtime with several providers of several countries in a Python based project.

Skills: JavaScript Node.js Vue.js Python FastAPI

Software Engineer and Teaching assistant @ Galileo University

Jan 2019 - Nov 2022 // Guatemala, Guatemala

- Developed a college level web system using JavaScript libraries and frameworks which is and has been used in several Computer Science courses by hundreds of users for the administration of class assignments and to provide the students the best possible learning experience.
- Supported students in laboratories building algorithms when teaching them important basic concepts using programming languages.
- Developed and carried out laboratory activities for 4 different Computer Science courses.
- ▶ Implemented teaching guides independently for classrooms of over 25 students.

Skills: Java Python HTML JavaScript Libraries University Teaching

Languages

Spanish English

Main skills

Languages

JavaScript (ES6), TypeScript, HTML, CSS/Sass, GraphQL, Python

Libraries, Frameworks & Database

React.js, Vue.js, Ionic, Storybook, Apollo Client, Bootstrap, MUI, Semantic UI, jQuery, Node.js, Express.js, Next.js, FastAPI, Graphene-Python, Mendix, Serverless Framework, MongoDB, PostgreSQL

Design

Figma, InVision

Tools, Platforms & Services

Git, Heroku, Docker, GCP (Google Compute Engine, Google Storage), AWS (EC2, ECS, ECR, S3, CloudFront, Route53), GitHub actions/pages

Education

Galileo University

2017 - 2020 // Guatemala, Guatemala Bachelor of Science in Engineering in Systems, Informatics and Computer Science

Galileo University

2021 - 2022 // Guatemala, Guatemala Master's degree in operations research

Projects

Computer Science Educative Web Platform

Web app built with Node.js, EJS, Bootstrap, Express and MongoDB to manage different assignments, announcements and to provide interactive material for learning programming languages to 6 different classrooms with over 25 students each.

Interests

Basketball, play the guitar, play videogames, watch TV shows.